<dashboard>
  <label>Conceptual Search</label>
  <row>
    <html>
      <a class="btn btn-xtreme" href="xtreme_overview">
        <span class="icon-play"></span>  Overview
      </a>
      <a class="btn btn-xtreme" href="command_reference">
        <span class="icon-play"></span>  Command Reference
      </a>
      <a class="btn btn-xtreme" href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/?q=documentation">
        <span class="icon-play"></span>  Documentation
      </a>
      <a class="btn btn-xtreme" href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/?q=support_pages">
        <span class="icon-play"></span>  Support
</a>
      <!-- <span class="insetrt">Scianta Analytics Help</span> -->
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">An Introduction to Conceptual Search</span>
      </p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Concepts and Contexts</span>
      </p>
      <p>As humans, we tend to think conceptually. A concept can be characterized by a semantic term
        that represents it. Terms such as Tall, Short, Long, Early, Late, Fast, and Slow are
        meaningful to us because they represent concepts that we understand based on our historical
        experience. Let's think for a moment about the concept of <strong>tall</strong> as it
        relates to people. We share a common notion of what <strong>tall</strong> means, based upon
        our shared experience. If someone tells us a person is <strong>tall</strong>, we have a good
        understanding of what that means. </p>
      <p>Let's consider some examples:</p> Is Kareem Abdul Jabar <strong>tall</strong>? Certanly. Do
      you know exactly what his height is, in inches? Probably not, but we can all agree that he's
        <strong>tall</strong>.<br /> Was Napolean <strong>tall</strong>? No. In fact, he's become an
      icon for an alternate concept: <strong>short</strong>.<br /> Actor Brad Garrett? He's quite
        <strong>tall</strong>
      <br />Tom Cruise? By most measures, he is not <strong>tall</strong>.<br /> Osama bin Laden?
      People agree that he was very <strong>tall</strong>.<br />
      <p>Tall is not defined by some threshold parameter. Is someone who stands 6'8&quot; considered
        tall? Sure. How 'bout someone 5'11&quot;? Also tall. And 5'10&quot;? We'd probably agree
        that yes, 5'10&quot; is still considered tall. It may be less tall than Kareem, but still
        tall.</p>
      <p> Note that there is no threshold parameter that determines <strong>tall</strong> vs not
          <strong>tall</strong>. <strong>Tall</strong> is a <strong>Concept</strong>, not a
        threshold value. This turns out to true of most all concepts, from characterizations of
        height to network latency to sales performance to musical talent to public sentiment.<br />
        <br />In fact, we can graph a mathematical representation of the <strong>concept</strong> of
          <strong>tall</strong>. The graph in Figure 1 might be one definition of
          <strong>tall</strong>. Note that the X axis is Height, in inches, ranging from 48 inches
        to 84 inches, a fair guess at the range of heights we'd see in a large sample of humans. The
        Y axis depicts the degree of membership in this <strong>concept</strong> of
          <strong>tall</strong>. In our depection, a person who stands 60&quot; has zero membership
        in the concept of <strong>tall</strong>. Someone 84&quot; has a membership of 1, or 100%. In
        this scenario, an 84&quot; person is &quot;more tall&quot; than a 72&quot; person. If we
        were looking at the underlying fuzzy mathematics that represent our concept of
          <strong>tall</strong>, we'd say that 84&quot; has 100% membership in the set
          <strong>tall</strong>, while 72&quot; has a bit under 50%.</p>
      <p
        align="center"><img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/tall_set_600.png"
          width="400"
          height="220"
          alt="tall" /><br /> Figure 1</p>
      <p
        align="left"> A question arises here. Most people would agree that, among a large sample of
        humans, we think of 72&quot; as quite tall. The notion that 72&quot; has less than 50%
        membership in our concept of <strong>tall</strong> doesn't seem quite right. That's OK. This
        just means that the straight line function we drew to represent our concept of
          <strong>tall</strong> is probably not a very accurate representation of the concept. We
        can fix that. The graph in Figure 2 is another definition of our concept of
          <strong>tall</strong>. This one probably comes closer to an accurate representation of
        what we think of, when we think of <strong>tall</strong>.</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/tall_set_s_600.png"
          width="400"
          height="220" /><br /> Figure 2</p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Capturing Points of View: Contexts</span>
      </p>
      <p>When we're thinking about an idea like the <strong>height</strong> of people, we consider a
        number of related <strong>concepts</strong>. The <strong>concepts</strong>
        <strong>tall</strong> and <strong>short</strong> are two "conceptually coherent" terms that
        describe concepts relating to height. In Extreme Search, we call this conceptually coherent
        grouping of concepts a <strong>context</strong>. A <strong>context</strong> defines a
        particular view of the world based on the meaning of the terms that define it. Such a
          <strong>context</strong> can be seen in Figure 3.</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/height-s_600.png"
          width="400"
          height="220" /><br /> Figure 3 </p>
      <p>The <strong>context</strong>
        <em>height</em> in Figure 3 illustrates an important characteristic of
          <strong>terms</strong> within a <strong>context</strong>: that is, that terms or concepts
        often overlap. It it very possible for a value under analysis to have membership in more
        than one <strong> concept</strong>. In our example here, a person can be somewhat tall and
        somewhat short at the same time. This idea is true of most any <strong>context</strong>
        applying to most any knowledge domain. It embodies the way we, as humans, think of the world
        and it is an extraordinarily powerful tenent of cognitive computing.</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/height_demo_600.png"
          width="400"
          height="220" /><br /> Figure 4 </p>
      <p>Figure 4 illustrates another definition of the <strong>context</strong>
        <em>height</em>. This illustration is the display of a <strong>context</strong> called
          <em>height</em> which we've defined in Extreme Search for Splunk. Note that this
          <strong>context</strong> is comprised of five <tstrong>terms</tstrong>: tiny, short,
        typical, tall and gigantic. There's nothing particularly special about these five names.
        They simply have meaning to the author when describing the notion of <em>height</em>.
        They're defined by the user and represent that user's perspective with regard to the height
        of humans.</p>
      <p>In Extreme Search, we allow users to define contexts either with or without regard to a
        particular data set. These contexts are saved in Extreme Search and can be used to analyze
        subsequent data sets or the same data set in a various time ranges. A subject matter expert
        might define a context with which the staff of his company should analyze a particular
        knowledge domain. For examle, a network expert might define a <strong>context</strong>
        called <em>latency</em> that support personnel or a monitoring system would use when
        analyzing real time network performance. If the <strong>context</strong> was generated using
        baseline data, applying it in real time analysis would immediately identify anomolies,
        without the need to learn baseline behavior. Scianta's concept-based cognitive computing
        engine can quickly model baseline behavior without the need for more conventional
        parameteric machine learning.</p>
      <p><em>So this is pretty interesting. What does it get us?</em></p>
      <p><strong>Concepts</strong> and collections of them which we call
          <strong>Contexts</strong> are critical components in concept-based cognitive computing.
        They facilitate the ability to gain deep insight from your data by asking
          <em>qualitative</em>, rather than <em>quantitative</em> questions, and to ask those
        questions in natural language.</p>
      <span
        class="head4">Conceptual Coherence</span>
      <p>In our example of the linear (Figure 1) vs S-shaped (Figure 2) definitions of the term
          <strong>tall</strong>, we noted that the shape of the membership function for a
          <strong>term</strong> is significant. I fact, it is important that the shape of the
          <strong>term</strong> represent the linguistic meaning of the <strong>term</strong>. When
        we say <strong>tall</strong>, the set of values that have membership in that
          <strong>concept</strong> should make linguistic sense. In the same way that someone would
        be confused if you called Karrem Abdul Jabar <strong>short</strong> and Napolean
          <strong>tall</strong>, they can be confused if we define concepts in Extreme Search
        that don't make linguistic sense. It is also important that all <strong>terms</strong>
        defined in a <strong>context</strong> be conceptually coherent – that they share the same
        "universe of discourse". It would be confusing if one <strong>term</strong> dealt with
          <em>Time</em> and another dealt with <em>Distance</em>.</p>
      <span
        class="head2">Embracing Nuance: Hedges</span>
      <p><bold>Concepts</bold> and <strong>Contexts</strong> are the basis of Conceptual
        Search but they don't, on their own, support a very nuanced view of the world. A true
        Cognitive Computing system, a system designed to "think" like we do, needs to understand
        nuance.</p>
      <p>Scianta Extreme Search for Splunk employs the notion of "hedges" to capture nuanced
        variation to concepts. Hedges are linguistic modifiers, adjectives, that modify the
        meaning of a concept. To learn more about <strong>hedges</strong> and other methods
        employed by Extreme Search to embrace the nuance ot human thought, click on Learn More.</p>
      <a href="hedges">
        <img
          alt="Learn More"
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/learn_button.png" />
      </a>
      <p><span
          class="head4">Related Extreme Search Commands: </span></p>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="xsCloneConcept">xsCloneConcept</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsCloneContext">xsCloneContext</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsCreateContext">xsCreateContext</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsDeleteContext">xsDeleteContext</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsDisplayConcept">xsDisplayConcept</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsDisplayContext">xsDisplayContext</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsFindMemebership">xsFindMemebership</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsGenerateContext">xsGenerateContext</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsGetWhereCIX">xsGetWhereCIX</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsRenameContext">xsRenameContext</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsUpdateContext">xsUpdateContext</a></li>
        <li><a href="xsWhere">xsWhere</a></li>
      </ul>
      <br />
      <span
        class="head2">Learn More About Cognitive Computing</span>
      <p>To learn more about conceptual search and its place in cognitive computing, consider
        downloading <a
          href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/sites/default/files/SA-IDXR-REFERENCE-V01_Cognitive_Computing.pdf">
          Principles of Cognitive Computing by Earl Cox. Chief Scientist, Scianta Analytics</a></p>
      <p>You might also want to take a look at <a
          href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/?q=learn"
          target="_blank"> the <strong>Learn</strong> section of the Scianta Analytics web site.</a>
      </p>
      <p align="center">
        <span class="head5">Sciante Extreme Search for Splunk is part of the Scianta Analytics Cognitive
          Computing Suite</span>
        <br />
        <a href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/"
          target="_blank">
          <img alt="Scianta Analytics" src="/static/app/xtreme/images/Scianta_Analytics_150.png" />
        </a>
      </p>
      <p>VERSION: 20140310.4</p>
    </html>
  </row>
</dashboard>
