<dashboard>
  <label>Hedges and Synonyms</label>
  <row>
    <html>
      <a class="btn btn-xtreme" href="xtreme_overview">
        <span class="icon-play"></span>  Overview
      </a>
      <a class="btn btn-xtreme" href="command_reference">
        <span class="icon-play"></span>  Command Reference
      </a>
      <a class="btn btn-xtreme" href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/?q=documentation" target="_blank">
        <span class="icon-play"></span>  Documentation
      </a>
      <a class="btn btn-xtreme" href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/?q=support_pages" target="_blank">
        <span class="icon-play"></span>  Support
</a>
      <!--<span class="insetrt">Scianta Analytics Help</span>-->
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Embracing Nuance: Hedges</span>
      </p>
      <p><strong>Concepts</strong> and <strong>contexts</strong> are the basis of Conceptual
        Search but they don't, on their own, support a very nuanced view of the world. A true
        Cognitive Computing system, a system designed to "think" like we do, needs to understand
        nuance.</p>
      <p>Scianta Extreme Search for Splunk employs the notion of "hedges" to capture nuanced
        variation to concepts. Hedges are linguistic modifiers, adjectives, that modify the
        meaning of a concept. Currently, Extreme Search for Splunk supports the following
        linguistic <strong>hedges</strong>:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>about</li>
        <li>above</li>
        <li>after</li>
        <li>before</li>
        <li>close</li>
        <li>extremely</li>
        <li>generally</li>
        <li>not</li>
        <li>positively</li>
        <li>slightly</li>
        <li>somewhat</li>
        <li>very</li>
        <li>vicinity</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Hedges allow us to look for people who are "very tall" or network segments where network
        latency is "extremely long" or performance that is "not typical". Just like in natural
        language a <strong>hedge</strong> acts as an adjective to alter the meaning of a
          <strong>term</strong>. Remember that our concepts are characterized mathematically
        by a membership function. Hedges act to change the shape of a term's membership function in
        a way that is appropriate to the linguistic meaning of the hedge.</p>
      <p>Figure 1 illustrates a <strong>context</strong> pertaining to a common demonstration data
        set , the FAA flight statistics data set. The data set includes a record of flight
        characteristics for every domestic commerical airline flight in the United States,</p>
      <p>The <strong>context</strong> depicted is that of <em>ArrDelay</em>, the Arrival Delay of
        commercial flights. In this <strong>context</strong>, we've defined five
          <strong>terms</strong>: incredible, early, ontime, late and outrageous. As we've said, the
        terms used were defined by the user. In this case, the term "incredible" is used to describe
        flights where the arrival time was significantly earlier than scheduled. "Outrageous"
        describes flights where the arrival delay was very long. The "Ontime" term is characterized
        by a bell-shaped curve centered around the scheduled arrival time.</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/arrdelay_800.png" /><br /> Figure 1 </p>
      <p>The <strong>term</strong>
        <em>Ontime</em> is isolated in Figure 2. We'll use <em>Ontime</em> to illustrate the effect
        of various <strong>hedges</strong> on a target <strong>concept</strong>.</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/ontime_800.png" /><br /> Figure 2 </p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/extremely_ontime_800.png" /><br /> Figure 3 </p>
      <p>Figure 3 is a graph of the <strong>concept</strong> of <em>Ontime</em>, as modified by the
          <strong>hedge</strong>
        <em>extremely</em>. Note that the resulting <strong>hedged concept</strong>
        <em>Extremely Ontime</em> is more narrow, the resulting values closer to the scheduled
        arrival time at the center of the <em>Ontime</em> bell curve. This is linguistically
        consistent with what we mean when we say "Extremely Ontime".</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/somewhat_ontime_800.png" /><br /> Figure 4 </p>
      <p>Figure 4 is a graph of the <strong>concept</strong> of <em>Ontime</em>, as modified by the
          <strong>hedge</strong>
        <em>somewhat</em>. The resulting <strong>hedged concept</strong>
        <em>Somewhat Ontime</em> is wider, the resulting values deviating more from the scheduled
        arrival time at the center of the <em>Ontime</em> bell curve. This is also linguistically
        consistent with what we mean when we say "Somewhat Ontime".</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/not_ontime_800.png" /><br /> Figure 5 </p>
      <p>Figure 5 is a graph of the <strong>concept</strong> of <em>Ontime</em>, as modified by the
          <strong>hedge</strong>
        <em>not</em>. The resulting <strong>hedged concept</strong>
        <em>Not Ontime</em> is what we'd expect: the mathematical inverse of the
          <strong>term</strong>
        <em>Ontime</em>.</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/above_ontime_800.png" /><br /> Figure 6 </p>
      <p>If you were asked to draw the <strong>hedged concept</strong>
        <em>Above Ontime</em>, you'd probably draw something like Figure 6. This is the
          <strong>term</strong>
        <em>Ontime</em>, as modified by the <strong>hedge</strong>
        <em>above</em>. The <strong>hedge</strong>
        <em>Below</em> works in a similar fashion, encompasing values below the center of
          <em>Ontime</em>.</p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head4">Compound Hedges</span>
      </p>
      <p>Here things start to get interesting. As humans, we're used to thinking about concepts
        modified by any number of adjectives. For example, you might decide that the latest reality
        TV show is "not very watchable". Both <em>Not</em> and <em>Very</em> are
          <strong>hedges</strong> to the term <em>Watchable</em>. Scianta Extreme Search supports an
        unlimited number of <strong>hedges</strong> applied to a <strong>concept</strong>.</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/not_very_ontime_800.png" /><br /> Figure 7 </p>
      <p>The chart in Figure 7 depicts the <strong>compound hedge</strong>
        <em>Not Very</em> applied to the <strong>term</strong>
        <em>Ontime</em>. As we'd expect, the first <strong>hedge</strong>, <em>Very</em>, narrows
        the set. The second <strong>hedge</strong>, <em>Not</em>, inverts <em>Very</em>. Note that
        the hedge closest to the <strong>term</strong> is applied first.</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/very_not_ontime_800.png" /><br /> Figure 8 </p>
      <p>Just as in human thought, the order in which we apply linguistic modifiers affects the
        result. Figure 8 shows the result of <em>Very Not Ontime</em>. In this case, the
          <strong>hedge</strong>
        <em>Not</em> is applied first. Then the <strong>hedge</strong>
        <em>Very</em> is applied, making the results "more not" than without the <em>Very</em>
        <strong>hedge</strong>. As we see in Figure 9, this notion of an unlimited number of
          <strong>compound hedges</strong> can be taken to the extreme.</p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/highly_complex_800.png" /><br /> Figure 9 </p>
      <p>Figure 9 is the result of the following querry in Extreme Search for Splunk: <em>Quite
          Extremely Not Somewhat Close to Below Ontime</em>. If it makes your head hurt trying to
        figure out what this means, you're not alone. The takeaway is this: If you can dream it up,
        Extreme Search will search for it, right there in the Splunk search bar.</p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Broadening Our Vocabulary: Synonyms</span>
      </p>
      <p>Cognitive computing requires an understanding of human thought and the language used to
        describe that thought. Our baker's dozen <strong>linquistic hedges</strong> go a long way
        toward capturing the important linguistic modifiers used in human thought, as long as you
        speak English and know which words we've chosen to represent each hedge. That would not make
        for a particularly powerful Conceptual Search system. Human-Centered Computing should not
        require the user to understand which particular linguistic forms the system thinks are
        important. In order to better understand the linguistic forms the user has chosen, Extreme
        Search supports <strong>synonyms</strong>.</p>
      <p>If your were paying particularly close attention during the discussion of highly complex
          <strong>hedges</strong> in Figure 9, you may have picked up on the use of <em>Quite</em>
        in the <strong>hedged term</strong>
        <em>Quite Extremely Not Somewhat Close to Below Ontime</em>. You may have noticed that
        "quite" is not included in the Extreme Search list of hedge words. The word <em>quite</em>
        is treated by Extreme Search as a <strong>synonym</strong> for the <strong>hedge</strong>
        <em>somewhat</em>. The word "quite" is listed in a <strong>synonyms</strong> file called
          <code>synonyms.csv</code> which resides in the <code>xtreme/lookups/</code> directory. The
          <code>synonyms.csv</code> file is a simple two factor comma separated values table, with
        values stated as <code>word,hedge</code>. A reserved hedge word <code>"_noise"</code> allows
        the system to ignore noisewords such as "a", "an", "to" and "the". </p>
      <p>If you look at <code>synonyms.csv</code> you'll see the following two lines:</p>
      <code>quite,somewhat</code>
      <br />
      <code>to,_noise</code>
      <p>These two lines allow <em>quite</em> to be treated as <em>somewhat</em> and the phrase
          <em>close to</em> to be treated as <em>close</em>.</p>
      <p>The Extreme Search <code>synonyms.csv</code> file can be modified by the user. This allows
        Extreme Search for Splunk to be easily customized to support multiple languages as well as
        industry, company or use-case-specific <strong>hedges</strong>. Non-English
          <code>synonyms</code> files are availabe from Scianta Analytics.</p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head4">Related Extreme Search Commands: </span>
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsCloneConcept">xsCloneConcept</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsCloneContext">xsCloneContext</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsCreateContext">xsCreateContext</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsDeleteContext">xsDeleteContext</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsDisplayConcept">xsDisplayConcept</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsDisplayContext">xsDisplayContext</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsFindMemebership">xsFindMemebership</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsGenerateContext">xsGenerateContext</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsGetWhereCIX">xsGetWhereCIX</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsRenameContext">xsRenameContext</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsUpdateContext">xsUpdateContext</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          <a
            href="xsWhere">xsWhere</a>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <br />
      <span
        class="head2">Learn More About Cognitive Computing</span>
      <p>To learn more about conceptual search and its place in cognitive computing, consider
        downloading <a
          href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/sites/default/files/SA-IDXR-REFERENCE-V01_Cognitive_Computing_20130925.1docx.pdf">
          Principles of Cognitive Computing by Earl Cox. Chief Scientist, Scianta Analytics</a></p>
      <p>You might also want to take a look at <a
          href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/?q=learn"
          target="_blank"> the <strong>Learn</strong> section of the Scianta Analytics web site.</a>
      </p>
      <p
        align="center">
        <span
          class="head5">Sciante Extreme Search for Splunk is part of the Scianta Analytics Cognitive
          Computing Suite</span>
        <br />
        <a
          href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/"
          target="_blank">
          <img
            alt="Scianta Analytics"
            src="/static/app/xtreme/images/Scianta_Analytics_150.png" />
        </a>
      </p>
      <p>VERSION: 20130930.1</p>
    <p>Copyright 2013 Scianta Analytics LLC All Rights Reserved</p>
    </html>
  </row>
</dashboard>
