<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="application.css"?>
<dashboard>
  <label>Overview</label>
  <row>
    <html>
      <img
        src="/static/app/xtreme/images/ess_400.png" />
      <p>
        <a
          href="command_reference">
          <img
            alt="Jump to Command Reference"
            src="/static/app/xtreme/images/commandreference_button.png" />
        </a>
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/space.png" />
        <a
          href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/?q=documentation"
          target="_blank">
          <img
            alt="Support Site"
            src="/static/app/xtreme/images/doc_button.png" />
        </a>
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/space.png" />
        <a
          href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/?q=support_pages"
          target="_blank">
          <img
            alt="Support Site"
            src="/static/app/xtreme/images/support_button.png" />
        </a>
      </p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Introduction</span>
      </p>
      <p>Extreme Search is unique. Most Splunk apps are designed as separate apps or add-ons,
        working externally to Splunk to deliver solutions in a variety of vertical problem spaces.
        By contrast, Scianta Analytics Extreme Search works <strong>within</strong> Splunk,
        extending Splunk's Search Processing Language (SPL) with Scianta Analytics' proprietary
        cognitive computing technology. Extreme Search for Splunk transforms Splunk into an
        extraordinarily powerful cognitive-computing-based analytics platform.</p>
      <p>Like most Splunk apps, Extreme Search presents an application view, including documentation
        and dashboards. This page is being displayed from within that application view. The Extreme
        Search application view provides dashboards to assit in managing your implementation and
        enhance visualization. It includes a robust set of help pages, like this one, to give you a
        quick reference to the product's operation. It also provides direct links from within the
        app to Scianta Analytics' online documentation, tutorials and support.</p>
      <p> It is important to note that it is not necessary to use the Extreme Search application
        view to use Extreme Search. Since Extreme Search operates as an extension to Splunk's search
        language, it is available to any Splunk app. The Extreme Search binaries, which provide the
        product's core cognitive computing functionality, are compiled natively for each operating
        system and are distributed by Splunk along with conventional Splunk search commands, to
        operate in parallel on each indexer. If you run more than one operating system in your
        Splunk environment, you'll want to make sure you install the correct binaries for each
        OS.</p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head4">What is Extreme Search for Splunk Enterprise?</span>
      </p>
      <p> Scianta's <strong>Extreme Search Engine</strong> is an integrated collection of powerful
        cognitive-computing-based analytics functions engineered for speed and transportability. The
        suite provides fast, flexible, and comprehensive statistical reasoning, predictive analytics
        and conceptual query capabilies in any computing environment. <strong>Extreme Search for
          Splunk</strong> is an implementation of the Sciant Extreme Search Engine which is
        engineered specifically for Big Data using the Splunk platform. The engine is optimized to
        run multiple, parallel threads on each Splunk indexer and is compiled to operate natively in
        Linux, Windows or Mac OS. This allows <strong>Scianta Extreme Search for Splunk</strong> to
        deliver extraordinary performance, even on gigantic data sets. </p>
      <p>Extreme Search is, first and foremost, a powerful cognitive computing engine. It is
        designed to "think" the way you think and to "understand" concept-based queries written in
        natural language.</p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head4">Converse with your data™</span>
      </p>
      <p> Splunk is arguably the world's most powerful Big Data engine. <strong>Extreme Search for
          Splunk Enterprise</strong> transforms Splunk into the world's most powerful
        human-centered, cognitive computing platform for Big Data. Extreme Search understands
        concepts and semantic terms in the same way you understand them. This allows you to converse
        with your data the same way you converse with your co-workers, using powerful qualitative
        concepts in place of arcane quantitative parameters. </p>
      <p>Why is this important? Because it allows regular users to gain deep insight from their data
        simply by asking questions.</p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Command Categories</span>
      </p>
      <p>Extreme Search commands can be divided into three operational categories:</p>
      <ul>
        <span
          class="head5">
          <li>Conceptual Search</li>
        </span> Qualitative, concept-based data exploration. <span
          class="head5">
          <li>Statistical Reasoning</li></span> Powerful regression and correlation tools for data
        analysis. <span
          class="head5">
          <li>Predictive Analytics</li></span> State-of-the-art machine learning tools. </ul>
      <p>The <a
          href="command_reference">Command Reference</a> describes each command in each of the three
        categories.</p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Conceptual Search</span>
      </p>
      <span
        class="head4">Terminology</span>
      <p>To understand Extreme Search concept based search, it is useful to understand some
        terminology used in the product and its documentation:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Concept: </strong>An idea represented by a <strong>semantic term</strong>. In
          Extreme Search, these terms are usually user defined as part of a <strong>Context .
            </strong><em>Tall, Short, Fast and Slow are </em><strong>Terms</strong> used to describe
            <strong>Concepts</strong>.</li>
        <li><strong>Context: </strong>A collection of terms that form a conceptually coherent view
          of a knowledge domain. <em>Height</em> might be a <strong>Context</strong> comprised of
          the <strong>Terms</strong>
          <em>Tall</em> and <em>Short</em>. <em>Speed</em> might be a <strong>Context</strong>
          comprised of the <strong>Terms</strong>
          <em>Fast</em> and <em>Slow</em></li>
        <li><strong>Semantic Term</strong> or <strong>Term: </strong>A linguistic representation of
          a <strong>Concept</strong>. In the underlying cognitive computing engine that drives
          Extreme Search for Splunk, each <strong>Term</strong> is characterized by a <strong>Fuzzy
            Set</strong>. </li>
      </ul>
      <p>For an introduction to conceptual search, click on "Learn More". </p>
      <p>To discover more about conceptual search, its role in human-based cognitive computing and
        the science upon which Extreme Search is based, click on "Deep Dive" to download
          <strong>Volume 1: Principles of Cognitive Computing</strong>, Earl Cox, Chief Scientist,
        Scianta Analytics. (pdf)</p>
      <p>
        <a
          href="concept_intro">
          <img
            alt="Learn More"
            src="/static/app/xtreme/images/learn_button.png" />
        </a>
        <img
          src="/static/app/xtreme/images/space.png" />
        <a
          href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/sites/default/files/SA-IDXR-REFERENCE-V01_Cognitive_Computing.pdf"
          target="_blank">
          <img
            alt="Deep Dive"
            src="/static/app/xtreme/images/deepdive_button.png" />
        </a>
      </p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Statistical Reasoning</span>
      </p>
      <p>Scianta Extreme Search includes powerful statistical reasoning functions that facilitate
        analysis of very large data sets quickly and intuitively within Splunk. Extreme Search
        supports the following categories of Statistical Reasoning functions:</p>
      <ul>
        <span
          class="head5">
          <li>Linear Regression</li>
          <li>Non-linear Regression</li>
          <li>Auto Regression</li>
          <li>Correlation</li>
        </span>
      </ul>
      <p>Learn more about Statistical Reasoning in Extreme Search in the <a
          href="command_reference">Command Reference.</a></p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Predictive Analytics</span>
      </p>
      <p>Scianta Extreme Search for Splunk Enterprise is part of the Scianta Analytics Cognitive
        Computing Suite. Our Cognitive Computing Suite delivers industry-leading, proprietary
        cognitive modeling, machine learning and predictive analytics to the world of Big Data.
        Extreme Search for Splunk Enterprise includes concept-based predictive analytics functions
        that run natively, within Splunk.</p>
      <p>Learn more about Predictive Analytics in Extreme Search in the <a
          href="command_reference">Command Reference.</a></p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Using Extreme Search</span>
      </p>
      <p>We encourage you to review the Extreme Search <a
          href="command_reference">Command Reference.</a> Taken together, these commands deliver to
        Splunk users the power of Scianta Analytics' cognitive-computing-based conceptual search,
        stastical reasoning and predictive analytics technology natively, within the Splunk
        platform. As a query processor, the components can also be combined and used as a data
        filter to collect, filter, and rank information based on the qualitative semantics
        associated with each data element. Because Extreme Search is tightly integrated with Splunk,
        results are delivered alongside the results of native Splunk search commands.</p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head4">Using Extreme Search from the Splunk Search app</span>
      </p>
      <p>All Extreme Search functions may be entered as commands directly within Splunk Search.
        Results are returned within the Splunk web interface. It is not necessary to use an external
        interface or the Extreme Search app view. Some Scianta Analytics cognitive computing suites,
        such as the Scianta Analytics Studio, execute Extreme Search functions and display results
        through their own user interfaces. Please see the documentation for these systems to learn
        how they work with Extreme Search for Splunk.</p>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head4">Using Extreme Search from the Extreme Search application view</span>
      </p>
      <p>Extreme Search includes dashboards designed to make it easier to develop and apply concepts
        and contexts without the need to enter Splunk Search. The following dashboards are
        accessible from the <strong>Conceptual Search</strong> menu in the Extreme Search
        application view.</p>
      <ul>
        <span
          class="head5">
          <li>
            <a
              href="create_context">Contexts: Create Context</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a
              href="generate_context">Contexts: Generate Context</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a
              href="display_context">Contexts: Display Context</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a
              href="generate_semantic_term">Contexts: Generate Semantic Term</a>
          </li>
        </span>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <span
          class="head2">Documentation and Help</span>
      </p>
      <p>Detailed information about each Extreme Search command is provided within your Splunk
        environment by Splunk's interactive help system. In addition the Extreme Search application
        view includes <strong>Help</strong> pages like this one within the application view. Some
        important <strong>Help</strong> pages include:</p>
      <ul>
        <span
          class="head5">
          <li>
            <a
              href="command_reference">Extreme Search Command Reference</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            <a
              href="concept_intro">Introduction to Conceptual Search</a>
          </li>
        </span>
      </ul>
      <p>Complete documentation for Extreme Search for Splunk is available online in the <a
          href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/?q=learn"
          target="_blank"><strong>Learn</strong> section of the Scianta Analytics web site</a>.</p>
      <br />
      <p
        align="center">
        <span
          class="head5">Sciante Extreme Search for Splunk Enterprise is part of the Scianta
          Analytics Cognitive Computing Suite</span>
        <br />
        <a
          href="http://www.sciantaanalytics.com/"
          target="_blank">
          <img
            alt="Scianta Analytics"
            src="/static/app/xtreme/images/Scianta_Analytics_150.png" />
        </a>
      </p>
      <br />
      <p>VERSION: 20131001.1</p>
    </html>
  </row>
</dashboard>
